Essex Company Photographs 6633 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Essex Company Photographs
1872-1967
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Essex Company
6633 P
8.78 cubic feet
8.3 linear ft.
Albumen print, cartes-de-visite (card photographs), gelatin silver print, lithographs, photographs, photomechanical processes, photomechanical prints.
Photographs of water turbines, canal construction and repair, storm damage, as well as other subjects. Most of the photographs were taken in Lawrence, Massachusetts.
10096493
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, November 10, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, January 04, 2018
Biographical / Historical
The Essex Company was charted in 1845 to build a dam and canals on the Merrimack River to provide power for textile mills, with the intent to build a planned city, Lawrence, Massachusetts. The company also built several mills and mill machinery.
In the 1830s Daniel Saunders began buying land on either side of the Merrimack River between Lowell and Andover, in order control the water power rights. With his son, Daniel Saunders, Jr., his uncle, J. Abbot Gardiner, and John Nesmith, he established the Merrimack River Power Association. Saunders then approached the Lawrence brothers (Samuel, Amos, and Abbott) and the Boston Associates. The Boston Associates bought the Merrimack Water Power Association and renamed it the Essex Company.
When Lawrence was incorporated as a town in 1847 and a city in 1853, the Essex Company laid out the streets and built much of the infrastructure. The City Hall and churches were built on land donated by the Essex Company.
Unique among the mill towns in New England, Lawrence, Massachusetts, was planned and development controlled due to the fact that the Essex Company owned most of the land along both sides of the river. The company further controlled development by buying, jointly with Lowell's Proprietors of Locks and Canals, land and water rights along the Merrimack River up to Lake Winnipesaukee, in New Hampshire. This led to the Essex Company becoming a pioneer in water and sewage treatment, developing the United States' first slow sand filter for drinking water.
In 1979 a hydroelectric company acquired the Essex Company in order to make use of the dam.
The above organizational history was condensed from The Lawrence History Center's Administrative History for their Records of the Essex Company of Lawrence, Massachusetts, 1845-1987.
Scope and Contents
Photographs of water turbines, canal construction and repair, flooding from spring runoff (freshets), ice dams, various buildings in the Lawrence, Massachusetts, area. Also included are photographs of scenery, family groups, houses, and othe buildings. Hurricane and tornado damage are also pictured.
Boxes 1 through 10 of this collection are prints made from the glass plate negatives in Collection 6633 GPN.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6633 G: Essex Company Graphics 6633 GPN: Essex Company Glass Plate Negatives 6633: Essex Company Records 6633 PUBS: Essex Company Publications Records of the Essex Company of Lawrence, Massachusetts, 1845-1987, Lawrence History Center Immigrant City Archives an Museum, Lawrence, Massachusetts
Billboards; Canals--Design and construction; Chimneys; Combing and drawing-- Powered--Comber, Noble; Dams; Dams--Design and construction; Dams--Maintenance and repair; Disasters; Dwellings; Executives; Factories; Hampshire Street Bridge.; Hood School (Lawrence, Mass.); Housing; Labor--General; Labor--Male; Machine shops; Mayors; Public buildings; Railroad bridges; Railroads; Sailboats; School superintendents; Steamboats; Storms--Floods; Textile factories; Textile industry; Textile machinery; Textile manufacturers; Textile mills--Carding room; Textile mills--Combing room; Textile workers; Tornadoes; Transportation; Turbines; Hydraulic turbines; Water-power; Water-wheels; Bodwell House (Lawrence, Mass.); Boston (Mass.); Brattleboro (Vt.); Bristol (N.H.); Cambridge (Mass.); Canal Street (Lawrence, Mass.); City Hall (Lawrence, Mass.); Connecticut River (CT); Den Rock (Lawrence, Mass.); Franklin (N.H.); Franklin Falls (Franklin, N.H.); Franklin Falls Dam (N.H.); Haverhill (Mass.); Lawrence (Mass.); Lawrence (Mass.)--Officials and employees; Loring Street Bridge (Lawrence, Mass.); Ludlow (Mass.); Merrimack River (N.H. and Mass.); Merrimack River Dam (Mass.); Merrimack River Valley (N.H. and Mass.); Newfound Lake (N.H.); North Canal (Lawrence, Mass.); Pemigewasset River (N.H.); Pine Street (Lawrence, Mass.); Revere House (Lawrence, Mass.); Shawsheen River (Mass.); Spicket River (N.H. and Mass.); United States; Chabot, Fred.; Coolidge, Clarissa Baldwin, 1791-1841; Chandler, F. E.; Hale, Richard A.; Harris, Nelson.; Hoadley, J. C. (John Chipman), 1818-1886; Holmes, Thomas.; Houston, George, active 1826-1829; Kempton, C. W.; Lewis, E. Frank.; Mills, Hiram F. (Hiram Francis), 1836- 1921; Oliver, Henry K. (Henry Kemble), 1800-1885; O'Reilly, C. J.; O'Reilly, James L.; Page, J. H. W.; Rollins, John R. (John Rodman), 1817-1892; Storrow, Charles S.--(Charles Storer)--1809-1904; Tewksbury, Robert H. (Robert Haskell), 1833-; Whittier, Fred.; Atlantic Cotton Mills.; Atlantic Mills (Lawrence, Mass.); Ayer Mill (Lawrence, Mass.); Champion International Corporation; Eastern Connecticut Power Company.; Essex Company (Lawrence, Mass.); Everett Mills.; Farwell Bleachery (Lawrence, Mass.); George E. Kunhardt Corporation.; Holyoke Machine Co.; Lawrence Duck Company (Lawrence, Mass.); Lawrence Gas amp; Electric Co. (Lawrence, Mass.); Lawrence Gas Company (Lawrence, Mass.); Lawrence Machine Shop; Lawrence Tornado of 1890; Longfellow Bridge (Boston and Cambridge, Mass.); Lower Pacific Mills (Lawrence, Mass.); Ludlow Manufacturing Associates.; Merrimac Paper Company.; Merrimack Valley Country Club (Lawrence, Mass.); Munroe Felt and Paper Company.; Pacific Mills.; Pemberton Manufacturing Company.; Plymouth Fibre Mills.; S. Morgan Smith Co.; The James Leffel amp; Co.; Union Park (So. Lawrence, Mass.); United States Worsted Corp.; Upper Pacific Mills (Lawrence, Mass.); Washington Mills (Lawrence, Mass.); Wood Worsted Mill (Lawrence, Mass.); York Manufacturing Company (Saco, Me.); United States. Army. Corps of Engineers
10096493
- ATHM Box 1-3 - "A" #6-29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 3 and 4
- ATHM "B" - #1-36, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 7 and 8
- ATHM "C" - #1-41, 1892-1893 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 9 and 10
- ATHM Box 1 - most photos not numbered, 1892-1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 1 and 2
- ATHM Box 2 - A1067-1069 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6612 GPN, Box 4
- ATHM Box 3 - #1-14 - some unnumbered (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 5 and 6
- ATHM Box 6 - #1-20, 129-131, 1892-1915 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 11 and 12
- ATHM Box 7 - #14-32, 199-206, 1892-1904 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 13 and 14
- ATHM Box 8 - #227-259, 1892-1893 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 15 and 16
- ATHM Box 9 - #174-192, 259-276, 1892-1910 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 17 and 18
- ATHM Box 10 - #258-288, 1892-1918 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 19 and 20
- ATHM Box 11 - #289-307 -- P217.210N, 386N, 490N, 321N, 1905-1913 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 21 and 22
- ATHM Box 12 - #1-11, 180-204, 213-216, 1892-1914 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 23 and 24
- ATHM Box 13 - #121-167, 1893-1914 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 25 and 26
- ATHM Box 14 - #23-2 - 43, 168-174, 1892-1912 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 27 and 28
- ATHM Box 15 - #1-24, 84-115-2, 1895-1915 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 29 and 30
- ATHM Box 16 - #1-53, 61, 217, 1897-1911 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 31 and 32
- ATHM Box 17 - #17-34, 316, 1893-1911 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 33 and 34
- ATHM Box 18 - #35-80, P217.400N, 1892-1897 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 35 and 36
- ATHM Box 19 - #1-10, 73-79, 1895-1899 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 37 and 38
- ATHM Box 20 - #9-27-2, 101-120, 1900-1925 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 39 and 40
- ATHM Box 21 - #1-39, 1910-1927 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 41 and 42
- ATHM Box 22 - #105-145, unidentified, 1892-1914 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 43 and 44
- ATHM Box 23 - #146-177, 1892-1897 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 45 and 46
- ATHM Box 24 - #187-218, 1892-1897 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 47 and 48
- ATHM Box 25 - #219-262-2, 1897-1915 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 49 and 50
- ATHM Box 26 - #110, 119, 210, 263-295, 1892-1911 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 51 and 52
- ATHM Box 27 - #296-321, unidentified, 1892-1894 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 53 and 54
- ATHM Box 28 - #322-357, 1893 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 55 and 56
- ATHM Box 29 - #E1-40, 1892-1893 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 57 and 58
- ATHM Box 30 - #401-435, A24, F1-F5, 1892-1893 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 59 and 60
- ATHM Box 31 - #42-47, 437-480, 678, 1893-1898 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 61 and 62
- ATHM box 32 - #481-516, 789(?), 1892-1894 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 63 and 64
- ATHM Box 33 - #D1-41, 1894 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 65 and 66
- ATHM Box 34 - #551-583, 1894-1896 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 67 and 68
- ATHM Box 35 - #584-620, 1895-1896 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 69 and 70
- ATHM Box 33 - #621-651, 1895-1896 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 71 and 72
- ATHM Box 37 - #652-689, 694, 698, 1894-1897 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 73 and 74
- ATHM Box 38 - #121, 690-722, P217.69N (Box 7, Folder 5)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 75 and 76
- ATHM Box 39 - #723-753, 1894-1901 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 77 and 78
- ATHM Box 40 - #754-791, 1894-1896 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 79 and 80
- ATHM Box 41 - #792-825, 1894-1898 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 81 and 82
- ATHM Box 42 - #827-865, 1898-1899 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 83 and 84
- ATHM Box 43 - #867-899, 1892-1898 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 85 and 86
- ATHM Box 44 - #900-940, 1897-1899 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 87 and 88
- ATHM Box 45 - #942-980, 1897-1899 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 89 and 90
- ATHM Box 46 - #981-999, 1899-1900 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Box 91
- ATHM Box 47 - #1-28, 1920-1927 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 92 and 93
- ATHM Box 48 - All photos are unnumbered - no dates (Box 9, Folder 4)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 94 and 95
- ATHM Box 49 - All photos are unnumbered - no dates (Box 9, Folder 5)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 96 and 97
- ATHM Box 50 - All photos are unnumbered - no dates (Box 9, Folder 6)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 98 and 99
- ATHM Box 51 - #15, 31, 46-56, 102-156, 206, 259-271, 679, 682, 1894-1895 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 100 and 101
- ATHM box 52 - #1-40 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 102 and 103
- ATHM Box 53 - #1-21 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Boxes 104 and 105
- ATHM Box 54 - #1-18, P 304.1-.5 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Box 106
- ATHM Box 55 - #1-4,11, 217 a-d, 218, 219 a-c (Box 10, Folder 5)
  Prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, Box 107
- ATHM Misc. photos - some labeled, most not labeled, 1892-1916 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  Miscellaneous prints from glass plate negatives in 6633 GPN, from unknown boxes
- P 1111.39 - .40 -- Lawrence, Ma. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Item 1: Essex Company workers repairing the Lawrence Dam, Lawrence, Mass., 1981; black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Copy print of: Essex Company workers repairing the Lawrence Dam, Lawrence, Mass. Lawrence Eagle-Tribune (photographer). Gelatin silver print. Image depicts several Essex Company workers repairing the Lawrence Dam on the Merrimack River in Lawrence, Mass. The workers have been lowered almost to the foot of the falls to repair a wooden structure. 20.25 x 25.25 cm.
    Format: black and white photograph.
  - Item 2: Essex Company workers on the Lawrence Dam, Lawrence, Mass., 1982; black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Copy print of: Essex Company workers on the Lawrence Dam, Lawrence, Mass. Lawrence Eagle-Tribune, photographer. Gelatin silver print. Image depicts several Essex Company workers working on flashboards of the Lawrence Dam on the Merrimack River in Lawrence, Mass. Photo taken in winter or early spring of 1982; workers in winter gear and ice visible just above flashboards. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
- P 217.82 -- Lawrence, Ma. Housing, black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Item 1: View of Kingston Street shanty, black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Lawrence, MA
- P 1062.46.2, P 1246.224.2, P 1246.224.3, P 1246.224.1, P 1246.226, P 1246.224.4, P 1246.224.5, P 1246.16, P 1246.224.1, P 1246.225, P 1246.224.5, P 2196, black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Item 1: Samuel Dale Stevens, reading "New England Homestead", black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Samuel Dale Stevens, reading "New England Homstead." Halftone, [1968]. Image depicts Samuel Dale Stevens (1859-1922) sitting in a chair, holding a copy of "New England Homestead" in his right hand. Stevens is dresssed in a dark, three-piece suit, white shirt, and tie. He wears a wedding ring on his left hand. Samuel Dale Stevens began working at M.T. Stevens (later M.T. Stevens & Sons Co.) in 1878; he became a partner with Nathaniel Stevens in 1885. See Collection 6896 P: Stevens Companies Photographs, for the original photograph from which this print was made. Fig. 5 from "S.D. Stevens and his spinning wheel collection," by Horatio Rogers, published in Essex Institute Historical Collections, January 1969, pp. 31-36. Copy A. 15.5 x 23.5 cm.
  - Item 2: Samuel Dale Stevens, reading "New England Homestead", black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Samuel Dale Stevens, reading "New England Homstead." Halftone, [1968]. Image depicts Samuel Dale Stevens (1859-1922) sitting in a chair, holding a copy of "New England Homestead" in his right hand. Stevens is dresssed in a dark, three-piece suit, white shirt, and tie. He wears a wedding ring on his left hand. Samuel Dale Stevens began working at M.T. Stevens (later M.T. Stevens & Sons Co.) in 1878; he became a partner with Nathaniel Stevens in 1885. See Collection 6896 P: Stevens Companies Photographs, for the original photograph from which this print was made. Fig. 5 from "S.D. Stevens and his spinning wheel collection," by Horatio Rogers, published in Essex Institute Historical Collections, January 1969, pp. 31-36. Copy B. 15.5 x 23 cm.
  - Item 3: Construction of Franklin Falls Dam, Franklin, N.H., 1941; black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Construction of Franklin Falls Dam, Franklin, N.H. Gelatin silver print snapshot, 1941. Image depicts the construction of the Franklin Falls Dam in Franklin, N.H. This photo, taken May 20, 1941, shows the rock berm on the left bank in the rear of the dam. Numerous cars and trucks parked in the foreground; several cranes visible in the middle ground. The dam was constructed by the Army Corps of Engineers for flood control of the Pemigewasset River; construction began in November 1939 and was completed in October 1943. The Pemigewasset River joins with the Winnipesaukee River about three miles downstream to form the Merrimack River. See Item 4, in this folder, for an almost identical view. 13.25 x 8.5 cm.
  - Item 4: Construction of Franklin Falls Dam, Franklin, N.H., 1941; black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Construction of Franklin Falls Dam, Franklin, N.H. Gelatin silver print snapshot. Image depicts the construction of the Franklin Falls Dam in Franklin, N.H. This photo, taken May 20, 1941, is taken from a slightly different angle than Item 3, in this folder. Over the roof of the building at the left is the entrance channel to the waste gates. Numerous cars and trucks parked in the foreground; several cranes visible in the middle ground. The dam was constructed by the Army Corps of Engineers for flood control of the Pemigewasset River; construction began in November 1939 and was completed in October 1943. The Pemigewasset River joins with the Winnipesaukee River about three miles downstream to form the Merrimack River. 13.25 x 8.5 cm.
  - Item 5: Construction of Franklin Falls Dam, Franklin, N.H., showing bridge in background, 1941; black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Construction of Franklin Falls Dam, Franklin, N.H., showing bridge in background. Gelatin silver print snapshot. Image depicts the construction of the Franklin Falls Dam in Franklin, N.H. This photo, taken May 20, 1941, shows the intake to the waste gate at the extreme left over the roof of the building. This photo shows bridge in the background. The waste gates are at the end of the curved wall. Cars and trucks parked in the foreground. The dam was constructed by the Army Corps of Engineers for flood control of the Pemigewasset River; construction began in November 1939 and was completed in October 1943. The Pemigewasset River joins with the Winnipesaukee River about three miles downstream to form the Merrimack River. 13.25 x 8.5 cm.
  - Item 6: Billboard describing the construction of the Franklin Falls Dam, Franklin, N.H., 1941; black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Billboard describing the construction of the Franklin Falls Dam, Franklin, N.H. Gelatin silver print snapshot. Image depicts a billboard that describes the construction of the Franklin Falls Dam in Franklin, N.H. Billboard shows the process of construction and gives statistics regarding the project. Note the probable completion date of June 30, 1942. The dam was constructed by the Army Corps of Engineers for flood control of the Pemigewasset River; construction began in November 1939 and was completed in October 1943. The Pemigewasset River joins with the Winnipesaukee River about three miles downstream to form the Merrimack River. This photo was taken on May 20, 1941. 13.25 x 8.5 cm.
  - Item 7: Partially completed Franklin Falls Dam, Franklin, N.H., 1941; black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Partially completed Franklin Falls Dam, Franklin, N.H. Gelatin silver print snapshot. Image depicts the ongoing construction of the Franklin Falls Dam in Franklin, N.H. The waste gates are at the extreme right; at the extreme left is the partially completed dam. Several cranes are visible in the photo; piles of lumber and ohter construction materials are in the fore- and middle ground. This photo taken May 20, 1941. The dam was constructed by the Army Corps of Engineers for flood control of the Pemigewasset River; construction began in November 1939 and was completed in October 1943. The Pemigewasset River joins with the Winnipesaukee River about three miles downstream to form the Merrimack River. 13.25 x 8.5 cm.
  - Item 8: Newfound Lake, Bristol, N.H., 1941; black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts Newfound Lake in Bristol, N.H., looking north from the southerly end of the lake. Photo taken May 20, 1941. 13.25 x 8.5 cm.
  - Item 9: Lawrence Dam, 1941; black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Gelatin silver print snapshot, May 20, 1941. Image depicts a view of the Lawrence Dam on the Merrimack River in Lawrence, Mass., taken May 20, 1941 at 7:30 pm. Written on reverse: "Lawrence Dam May 20, 1941 7:30 PM About 5 inches of water over flash boards." 13 x 8.5 cm.
  - Item 10: John R. Rollins, paymaster for the Essex Company, black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Yeaw & Co., No. 166 Essex Street, Lawrence, Mass. Albumen print carte de visite, [1863-66?]. Image depicts a bearded Rollins standing, with his arms crossed, in a Civil War (Union) uniform with ceremonial sword hanging at his left side. 5.5 x 8.75 cm. (w/out mount); 6 x 10 cm. (w/mount).
- P 217.52-.63, .65-.71, black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: View of Union Park, 1915; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
    South Lawrence, MA
  - Item 2: View of Union Park, 1915; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
    South Lawrence, MA, with Ayer Mill and clock tower in background
  - Item 3: View of Union Park, 1915; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Item 4: View of Union Park, 1915; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Item 5: View of Union Park, 1915; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Item 6: View of Union Park, 1915; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Item 7: View of Union Park, 1915; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Item 8: View of Union Park, 1915; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Item 9: View of Union Park, 1915; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Item 10: View of Union Park, 1915; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Item 11: View of Union Park, 1915; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Item 12: View of Union Park, 1915; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Item 13: View of construction of the Washington Chimney, black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
    At the Washington Mills, Lawrence, MA
  - Item 14: Essex Company's North Canal., 1897; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
    General view looking down Canal Street from point opposite Pacific Store House, June 1897
  - Item 15: Essex Company's North Canal., 1897; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Item 16: View of Upper Pacific Mills, black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)